What other problems do we need to solve
실제 세상에 있는 순차적 의사 결정을 하기 위해
to enable real-world sequential decision-making.
우리가 풀어야 할 다른 문제들은 무엇이 있을까요
Reinforcement learning deals with the problem of maximizing rewards.
강화학습은 보상을 최대화하는 문제를 다루므로
So it assumes that it can interact with a system,
그래서 강화학습은 시스템과 상호 작용할 수 있다고 가정합니다.
receives ground truth reward supervision although not ground truth outputs,
강화학습은 ground truth은 아니지만 ground truth 보상에 대한 지도를 받고
and then has to figure out the right outputs the right actions to take
그 보상들을 최대화 하기 위한
to maximize those rewards.
행동들을 할 수 있도록 하는 적절한 출력을 알아내야 합니다.
But this is not the only problem that matters for sequential decision making.
그러나 이것만이 순차적 의사 결정에서의 유일한 문제는 아닙니다.
More advanced topics which we'll cover in this course
이번 수업에서 다룰 심화 주제들로는
will include things like learning reward functions from example,
예들로 부터 보상 함수를 배우는
which is called inverse reinforcement learning.
inverse reinforcement learning (역강화학습)이 있습니다.
Transfering knowledge between different domains
서로 다른 도메인 간에 지식을 전수하는
thus it is sometimes called transfer learning and meta learning
transfer learning(전이학습) 또는 meta learning(메타학습)도 있습니다.
and it deals with a question of how do you use past experience for different but related tasks
이 방법론은 이전에 해결할 수 없었던 새로운 과제를 해결하기 위해
to solve new tasks that you haven't been able to solve before.
이 과제와는 다르지만 관련된 과거 경험을 어떻게 사용하는지에 대한 질문을 다룹니다.
Learning to predict and using prediction to act
예측을 학습하고 예측을 사용하여 행동하는 것을
this is often referred to as model based reinforcement learning
model based reinforcement learning (모델 기반 강화 학습)이라고 합니다.
where instead of learning behaviors directly instead what you attempt to learn
행동을 직접 배우는 것 대신에
is some representation of how the world works
세상이 어떻게 작동하는지에 대한 표현들을 학습합니다.
which can then be used for planning or for synthesizing into a policy.
이 표현들은 policy를 만들거나 계획을 세우는데 사용될 수 있습니다.
Here's one question that we'll deal with in the second half of the course.
다음으로는 수업의 후반부에서 다룰 한가지 질문입니다.
Where do rewards come from?
보상은 어디에서 올까요?
In some cases it seems very natural for that grasping robot that we talked about at the beginning
처음에 이야기한 grasping robot 같은 경우에는
its reward clearly should depend on whether it grasps something successfully.
무언가를 잘 잡는지에 따라 보상이 결정되는 것이 매우 당연합니다.
If you're training a dog some trick
만약 당신이 개를 훈련시키고 있다면,
maybe the dog's reward function depends on the treat that it gets.
아마도 개의 보상 함수는 받는 간식에 달려 있을 것입니다.
But more generally where they come from
그러나 보상이 어디에서 왔는지 좀 더 확장해봅시다.
if you're learning an atari game maybe the answer is obvious
아타리 게임을 배워보면 아마도 답은 명확할 것입니다.
but what if you need a robot to learn to pour a glass of water
하지만 만약 물 한 컵 부어주는 로봇이 필요하다면,
this is something that any child could probably do but
이것은 어떤 어린이라도 할 수 있는 일이지만,
for a robot you would need an entire perception system
로봇의 경우에는 컵에 물을 잘 부었는지
just to understand whether the water has been poured into the glass correctly.
판단하기 위해 통합적인 인지 시스템이 필요합니다.
There was a paper that some of my colleagues at the berkeley ai research lab
버클리 인공지능 연구소의 동료들이
put out a few years back
몇 년 전에 발표한 논문이 있었습니다.
and in their paper they had this comment at the end as human agents
그리고 그 논문 마지막 부분에서 human agents인 우리는
we're accustomed to operating with rewards
보상을 기반으로 수행하는데 익숙하지만
that are so sparse that we only experience them once or twice in a lifetime if at all.
보상은 너무 희박해서 평생에 한 두 번만 경험하게 된다고 말하고 있습니다.
And of course somebody on reddit responded to this by saying "i pity the author".
그리고 reddit의 누군가는 "나는 저자가 불쌍하다"라고 했습니다.
But while somewhat tragic this statement does reflect a lot of tasks
그러나 다소 비극적이지만, 이 말은 우리가 현실에서
that we really do have to solve in the real world
실제로 해결해야 하는 많은 과제들을 설명해주고 있습니다.
those of you that are taking this class now, you know
지금 이 수업을 듣는 분들은
one might say that you're taking this class because you will receive some delayed reward later down the line
나중에 지연된 보상을 받을 것이기 때문에 이 수업을 듣는다고 말할 수도 있습니다.
when you graduate with a degree in computer science
여러분이 컴퓨터 과학 학위로 졸업할 때
but you can't possibly have learned to
시행착오를 통해 학위를
receive degrees in computer science from trial and error
취득하지는 못할 것입니다.
because that's probably only something you're going to do once in your lifetime.
학위 취득은 일생에 한 번뿐일 일이기 때문입니다.
We know in the brain that there are structures that are responsible
우리는 뇌에 기저 신경절(basal ganglia)과 같은 보상 메커니즘을
for reward mechanisms like the basal ganglia
담당하는 구조가 있다는 것을 알고 있습니다.
and these are complex structures so the rewards in the brain are not these simple switches
그리고 이는 복잡한 구조로 되어 있어서 뇌에서 일어나는 보상 체계는
that you get for very specific and very simple events
특정한 간단한 사건을 다루는 스위치 같지 않습니다.
there is a lot of brain machinery that is responsible for assigning appropriate rewards
적절한 행동을 했을 때에 대한 적절한 보상을 주는
to appropriate behaviors
뇌의 기제들이 많이 있습니다.
and it's not difficult to see why this is necessary.
이것이 왜 필요한지에 대해 알아보는 것은 어렵지 않습니다.
besides the examples with college degrees
대학 학위 예 외에도
You could imagine a more naturalistic example like a cheetah trying to chase down a gazelle
가젤을 쫓는 치타와 같은 더 자연스러운 예를 상상할 수 있습니다.
well it seems pretty unlikely that the cheetah just randomly flails around until it accidentally manages to maul a gazelle
치타가 아무렇게나 날뛰다가 우연히 가젤을 낚아채게 되고
and from that figures out that because it received a reward should do that behavior more often
이 사건으로부터 그런 행동을 더 자주 해야 보상을 얻는다라는 것을 알게 된다는 것은 말이 안됩니다.
this behavior is so difficult for the shooter to perform
치타가 수행하기에 꽤 어려운 행동이기 때문입니다.
there must be some more sophisticated more detailed guiding mechanism
이 행동을 하게 된 원인에 대한
that caused it to acquire this behavior
더 정교하고 자세한 안내가 필요합니다.
So are there other forms of supervision
그래서 이런 매우 드물고 희소한 보상들 외에
besides these kind of very sparse very occasional rewards
다른 형태의 supervision(지시)가 있을까요?
well you could imagine acquiring some representation of behavior from demonstrations
데모로부터 어떤 행동들의 표현들을 얻을 수 있습니다.
either by directly copying the behavior that you observed
관찰한 행동을 직접적으로 따라하거나
or by inferring from that behavior a more detailed reward function
또는 그 행동에서 더 자세한 보상 함수를 추론하면서 말이죠.
which is called inverse reinforcement learning
이 방법이 inverse reinforcement learning (역강화학습)입니다.
So perhaps the cheetah saw an older more experienced cheetah chasing down a gazelle
그래서 아마도 그 치타는 어떤 노련한 치타가 가젤을 쫓는 것을 보았을 것이고
and figured out from from watching that
그때 보상을 받을 수 있는
that there are some rewarding behaviors that can happen down the line.
몇 가지 행동들이 있다는 것을 깨달았을 것입니다.
You could also learn from observing what happens in the world
또한, 세상에 일어나고 있는 일들을 관찰하고 배우면서
so you could for instance learn to predict future events
미래 사건들을 예측하는 것을 학습할 수 있습니다.
if you learn something about the causal structure about the physics of the real world
만약 실제 세상의 물리적 인과 구조에 대해 뭔가를 배운다면,
you can use that knowledge, that learned knowledge,
배운 지식을 가지고
to figure out which actions will lead to desired outcomes.
어떤 행동이 원하는 결과로 이어지는 지 파악할 수 있습니다.
Unsupervised learning methods take care of part of this problem
비지도 학습 방법이 이 문제의 일부를 다룹니다.
You could also learn from other tasks
또한, 다른 과제로부터도 배울 수 있습니다.
so maybe you haven't solved this particular task at hand, maybe you've never obtained
아마 이 특정 과제는 해결하지 못했을 수도 있지만,
a degree in computer science before
이처럼 아마 이전에 컴퓨터 공학 학위를 받은 적은 없겠지만,
but you've performed other tasks that are structurally related
그러나 구조적으로 관련된 다른 과제를 수행했었을 겁니다.
you went to a high school perhaps where you obtain a high school degree
고등학교에 다니고 고등학교 학위를 취득했을 것입니다.
and from that you've understood something about the structure of how you get education how you pass tests and so on.
그리고 그때 어떻게 교육을 받는지, 어떻게 시험을 통과하는 지에 대해 어느 정도 이해했을 겁니다.
this is sometimes referred to as transfer learning
이것을 transfer learning(전이학습)이라고 합니다.
A more sophisticated version is called meta learning which actually uses past tasks
보다 정교한 버전으로는 meta learning(메타 학습)이라고 하는데,
not just to become better at new tasks
단순히 새로운 일을 잘하는 것뿐만 아니라
but actually become better at acquiring a new task
실제로 새로운 일을 습득하는 것을 더 잘하게 됩니다.
actually learning how to learn
진짜로 배우는 법을 배우는 것이죠.
and this is hopefully something that you've all done through past classes that you've taken.
이건 이전 수업을 통해 모두 배운 것들입니다.
Methods in these categories have been showing you some pretty impressive things so
이 카테고리에 있는 방법론들은 꽤 인상적인 것들을 보여주었습니다.
This is a video released by nvidia about four years ago
이것은 약 4년 전에 nvidia에서 공개한 영상인데요.
showing an imitation learning system for autonomous driving so this is not a reinforcement learning system
자율 주행을 위한 imitation learning(모방 학습) 시스템을 보여주고 있습니다. 강화 학습 시스템은 아니기에,
it doesn't learn from reward supervision it actually learns by attempting to mimic human drivers
reward supervision으로 배우지 않고 실제 인간 운전자를 모방하기 위해 학습합니다.
and we'll talk about imitation learning in a lot of detail next week
다음 주에 imitation learning(모방 학습)에 대해 자세히 이야기하겠습니다.
But observing other agents performing useful behaviors can be used for more
그런데, 유용한 행동을 하는 다른 에이전트들을 관찰하는 것은
than just direct mimicry direct imitation.
직접 모방하는 것 이상으로 활용될 수 있습니다.
This is a video showing an experiment in child psychology.
이건 아동 심리학 실험 영상입니다.
so here this guy is trying to put some books away
한 남자는 책을 치워 두려고 합니다.
and this child is going to watch what he's doing now that
그리고 이 아이는 이 사람을 흉내내지 않고
the child is not going to mimic this person
그가 하는 일을 지켜볼 것입니다.
what the child is going to do instead
대신에 아이는
is infer what this person is trying to do
이 사람이 하려고 하는 것이 무엇인지를 추론하고,
and then perform the tasks that they are attempting to do but more optimally.
이 사람이 하려고 하는 작업을 수행하지만, 더 최적의 방법으로 하게 됩니다.
So if you can observe somebody doing something
그래서 누군가 무엇을 하는 것을 관찰하고,
and figure out their goal perhaps you can actually accomplish their goal more effectively
그 사람이 하려는 목표를 알게 되면, 아마도 당신은 그 목표를 더 효과적으로 수행할 수 있을 겁니다.
by performing a little bit of reinforcement learning with that inferred goal
추론한 목표를 가지고 약간의 강화 학습을 하면서 말이죠.
and of course we can turn this into real world algorithms
물론, 이것을 실제 세상에서의 알고리즘으로 바꿀 수 있습니다.
so here this is an experiment done by Chelsea Finn
여기 보이는 이것은 Chelsea Finn이 진행한 실험입니다.
Chelsea is demonstrating to the robot a behavior for pouring from one cup to another
Chelsea는 한 컵에서 다른 컵으로 액체를 붓는 로봇을 시연했습니다.
and the robot is not just going to copy this behavior
이 로봇은 단지 행동을 따라하는 것 뿐만 아니라
but it's going to do, it's going to infer its goal
목표를 추론하게 됩니다.
which is to position the orange cup or the yellow cup
주황색 컵이나 노란색 컵을 어디에 놔야하는지를 말이죠.
and then pour into a cup at a different location
그런 다음, 액체를 붓는 물리적인 방식이 조금 다를 수 있는
the way that it does the physical pouring might be a little bit different
다른 위치에 있는 컵에 붓습니다.
but the goal will be the same
하지만 목표는 같을 겁니다.
Prediction is a pretty fundamental component of human animal control and decision making
예측은 사람(동물) 제어와 의사결정에 있어서 매우 기본적인 구성 요소입니다.
this quote says the idea that we predict the consequences of our motor commands
이 인용구에서, 우리가 motor commands (운동명령)의 결과를 예측한다는 생각이
has emerged as an important theoretical concept in all aspects of sensory motor control
sensory motor control(감각 운동통제)의 모든 측면에서 중요한 이론적 개념이 되었다고 말합니다.
Prediction for real world control is something that is studied
실제 세계에서의 제어에 대한 예측은
in the domain of model-based reinforcement learning.
model-based reinforcement learning (모델 기반 강화 학습)에서 연구 중입니다.
so here's an example from some work by Frederick Ebert who's a student here at UC Berkeley
여기 UC Berkeley의 학생인 Frederick Ebert의 연구인데요.
here we have a robot that is interacting with objects in its environment
여기에 주변 환경의 물체와 상호 작용하는 로봇이 있습니다.
and it's certain interacting very purposefully it's sort of playing with objects just kind of moving around, randomly pushing things around,
매우 의도적으로 상호 작용하는 것은 확실합니다. 마치 물건들을 가지고 놀듯, 물건들 주위에 돌아다니고 무작위로 물건들을 밀죠.
and that experience is going to be used not to learn a policy for doing any particular thing
그리고 이 경험은 특정 일을 하기 위한 policy를 배우는 데 사용되지 않을 것입니다.
but it's said to learn a model that predicts what will happen next
하지만 로봇이 지금 무엇을 보고 있고 미래에 어떤 행동을 취할지를 고려 할 수 있다면,
given what the robot is seeing now and what actions is considering taking in the future.
그 다음 무슨일이 일어날지 예측하는 모델을 배운다고 할 수 있습니다.
So each row in this illustration
그래서 이 사진들의 각 행은
starts from the same starting image
동일한 시작 이미지에서 시작하는데요.
but predicts the outcome for different actions
그러나 다른 행동들에 대한 결과들을 예측합니다.
and this particular model is directly predicting the pixels that the robot will see.
그리고 이 모델은 로봇이 보는 픽셀들로부터 직접적으로(directly) 예측합니다.
so it's predicting that if the, you know, in the top row
따라서 맨 위 행의 사진들이
if the robot arm moves up that's those are the pixels if it moves down the pixels are different and so on
로봇 팔이 위로 움직이면 보이는 픽셀들입니다. 만약 로봇팔이 아래로 움직이면 픽셀들이 달라지겠죠.
and of course as you can see in the bottom row
물론 아래 행에서 볼 수 있듯이,
it correctly predicts that if the arm moves to the right then will also push some objects
모델은 팔이 오른쪽으로 움직이면 물체들이 밀릴 것이라고 올바르게 예측합니다.
now the predictions are kind of blurry they're quite uncertain
예측은 다소 명확하지 않지만,
but they count for some basic properties about how objects will behave
물체들이 어떻게 움직일지에 대한 몇 가지 기본 속성을 고려합니다.
and then we can give the robot a goal we can tell it
그리고 로봇에게 목표를 줄 수도 있습니다.
take this object located at this red dot
이 빨간 점에 위치한 물체를
and move it to the position of this green dot
이 녹색 점의 위치로 옮기라고 말이죠.
and by directly predicting the outcomes of its actions
그리고 그 행동의 결과를 바로 예측함으로써
the robot can plan out a series of actions that will move the object in the right way
로봇은 물체를 잘 옮길 수 있는 일련의 행동을 계획할 수 있습니다.
and here's the the result of actually executing that behavior
실제로 실행한 결과는 다음과 같습니다.
we could use predictive models for more sophisticated behaviors this is worked by Annie
보다 정교한 행동들에도 예측 모델을 사용할 수 있습니다.
she who was an undergraduate here at berkeley
이것은 버클리 학부생이었던 Annie의 연구인데요.
and what Annie did is extended the system to use a predictive model
그녀는 예측 모델을 사용하여 도구 사용 방법을 계획하도록
to plan how to use tools
시스템을 확장했습니다.
so here a robot could plan to pick up a sponge and use that sponge to move some objects
여기 이 로봇은 스펀지를 집고 이것을 사용하여 물체들을 옮길 계획을 세울 수 있습니다.
it could pick up a little hook and use that hook to move this blue object to the top
또한, 작은 갈고리를 집고 이를 이용하여 파란색 물체를 위로 이동시킬 수 있습니다.
and it could even improvise by figuring out that it can use a water bottle to sweep some trash to the edge of the bin
그리고 물병을 사용하여 쓰레기통의 가장자리로 쓰레기들을 쓸 수 있다는 것을 알아내고 바로 할 수도 있습니다.
We can also use predictive models for other tasks
또한 예측 모델을 다른 작업에 사용할 수 있습니다.
so this is some work by Kaiser at all which focused on using predictive models to play video games
비디오 게임을 위한 예측 모델에 초점을 맞춘 Kaiser의 연구인데요.
so here in the left you see the predictions made by the model for this particular video game
왼쪽에서 이 특정 비디오 게임에 대한 모델이 만든 예측을 볼 수 있고,
and in the middle you can see the real images the image on the right just shows the difference between the two
가운데에서 실제 이미지를 볼 수 있습니다. 오른쪽 이미지는 둘의 차이를 보여줍니다.
the predictions are not actually perfectly correct
사실, 예측은 완벽하게 정확하지 않습니다.
so here for instance the real image had three opponents the predictor one had only one
예를 들어, 실제 이미지에는 세 명의 상대가 있지만 예측 이미지에는 한 명만 있습니다.
but they're kind of qualitatively right so the model predicts that
그러나 예측들은 내용상으로는(qualitatively) 맞습니다.
when you kick the opponents they'll disappear
모델은 당신이 상대방을 차면 그들이 사라질 것이고,
and that you'll get variable numbers of opponents coming at you
당신에게 다양한 수의 상대방들이 나타날 것이라고 예측합니다.
but of course it's not perfect so sometimes it has a few issues
물론 완벽하지 않으므로 때때로 몇 가지 문제가 있습니다.
In this case, you'll have the example of boxing game the video we'll repeat shortly
이 경우 복싱 게임 예가 있는데요. 짧게만 봅시다.
in this boxing game there are two boxers
이 권투 경기에는 복서가 두 명 있습니다.
but they start getting blurry and this kind of second boxer appears
그런데 그들이 흐릿해지다가 두 번째 복서가 나타나게 됩니다.
and that second boxer then grows a third arm
이 두 번째 권투 선수는 점점 커지고 세 번째 팔이 나타납니다.
so there's something very strange going on here
여기에서 매우 이상한 일이 일어나고 있는데요.
something a little bit unusual basically the model is generalizing in ways
조금 이상하지만 기본적으로 모델이 일반화하고 있는 방식입니다.
that are ,you know, a little bit off
약간 다른 방식인거죠.